mikogo.com 2019-12-23

# The Mikogo Privacy Policy | www.mikogo.com

Snapview GmbH is particularly concerned about data protection. Our efforts in particular to meet the requirements of the European General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) and the German Federal Data Protection Act in its new version are primarily aimed at respecting your privacy and personal sphere.

For modern companies such as Snapview GmbH, the use of electronic data processing systems is indispensable nowadays. It goes without saying that we will do our utmost to comply with the legal regulations.

The Snapview GmbH website can be used without any indication of personal data. However, if the data subject wishes to make use of special services of our company via our website, it may be necessary to process personal data. If the processing of personal data is necessary and there is no legal basis for such processing, we generally obtain the consent of the data subject.

Under no circumstances will we sell or rent your personal information to third parties for their marketing or other purposes. If you do not agree with the provisions of the data protection declaration, please do not send any personal data to us.

## 1\. General Information, Definition of Terms

This data protection declaration is based on terms of the GDPR and should be easy to read and understand for every person. For this reason, we would like to explain various terms in advance:

**a) personal data  
**Personal data means any information relating to an identified or identifiable natural person (hereinafter “data subject”). An identifiable natural person is one who can be identified, directly or indirectly, in particular by reference to an identifier such as a name, an identification number, location data, an online identifier or to one or more factors specific to the physical, physiological, genetic, mental, economic, cultural or social identity of that natural person.

**b) data subject / person concerned  
**Data subject means any identified or identifiable natural person whose personal data are processed by the controller.

**c) processing  
**Processing means any operation or set of operations which is performed on personal data or on sets of personal data, whether or not by automated means, such as collection, recording, organization, structuring, storage, adaptation or alteration, retrieval, consultation, use, disclosure by transmission, dissemination or otherwise making available, alignment or combination, restriction, erasure or destruction.

**d) restriction of processing  
**Restriction of processing means the marking of stored personal data with the aim of limiting their processing in the future.

**e) Profiling  
**Profiling means any form of automated processing of personal data consisting of the use of personal data to evaluate certain personal aspects relating to a natural person, in particular to analyze or predict aspects concerning that natural person’s performance at work, economic situation, health, personal preferences, interests, reliability, behavior, location or movements.

**f) pseudonymization  
**Pseudonymization means the processing of personal data in such a manner that the personal data can no longer be attributed to a specific data subject without the use of additional information, provided that such additional information is kept separately and is subject to technical and organisational measures to ensure that the personal data are not attributed to an identified or identifiable natural person.

**g) controller  
**Controller means the natural or legal person, public authority, agency or other body which, alone or jointly with others, determines the purposes and means of the processing of personal data; where the purposes and means of such processing are determined by Union or Member State law, the controller or the specific criteria for its nomination may be provided for by Union or Member State law.

**h) processor  
**Processor means a natural or legal person, public authority, agency or other body which processes personal data on behalf of the controller.

**i) recipient  
**Recipient means a natural or legal person, public authority, agency or another body, to which the personal data are disclosed, whether a third party or not. However, public authorities which may receive personal data in the framework of a particular inquiry in accordance with Union or Member State law shall not be regarded as recipients; the processing of those data by those public authorities shall be in compliance with the applicable data protection rules according to the purposes of the processing.

**j) third party  
**Third party means a natural or legal person, public authority, agency or body other than the data subject, controller, processor and persons who, under the direct authority of the controller or processor, are authorized to process personal data.

**k) consent  
**Consent of the data subject means any freely given, specific, informed and unambiguous indication of the data subject’s wishes by which he or she, by a statement or by a clear affirmative action, signifies agreement to the processing of personal data relating to him or her.

## 2\. Information on the collection of personal data

(1) In the following we inform you about the collection of personal data when using our website. Personal data are all data that can be related to you personally, e.g. name, address, e-mail addresses, user behavior, etc.

(2) The person responsible pursuant to Art. 4 Para. 7 EU General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) is

Snapview GmbH  
represented by the Managing Directors Erik Boos, Mark Zondler  
Schwanthalerstraße 22  
80336 Munich  
Germany

Tel.: +49 89 / 5880 1133 – 0  
Fax: +49 89 / 5880 1133 – 9  
E-Mail: info@snapview.de  
Website: www.snapview.de

(3) Our data protection officer is:

Mr. LL.M. Sascha Weller, IDR – Institut für Datenschutzrecht  
Ziegelbräustraße 7  
85049 Ingolstadt  
Germany

Tel.: +49 89 / 5880 1133 – 8  
E-Mail: dsb@snapview.de  
Web: www.idr-datenschutz.de

(4) When you contact us via e-mail or a contact form, the information you provide (your e-mail address, your name and telephone number, if applicable) will be automatically stored by us to answer your questions and to our CRM system, which is provided by Salesforce Inc., based in the USA. Although Salesforce Inc. also operates servers within the EU, it cannot be ruled out that your data may be transferred and processed in a third country (e.g. the USA) or that your data stored within the EU may be accessed from third countries. Salesforce Inc. processes personal data under the EU-US Privacy Shield. We have also concluded a so-called data processing agreement with Salesforce Inc. in accordance with Art. 28 GDPR with EU standard contract clauses to ensure an appropriate level of data protection. A copy of this can be downloaded from https://www.salesforce.com/assets/pdf/misc/data-processing-addendum.pdf.  
All personal data voluntarily transmitted by a data subject to the data controller will be stored exclusively for the purpose of processing or contacting the data subject. We delete the data arising in this connection after the storage is no longer necessary or restrict the processing if there are legal storage obligations.

(5) If we wish to use contracted service providers for individual functions of our offer or use your data for advertising purposes, we will inform you below in detail about the respective processes. We will also specify the criteria for the storage period.

(6) As the data controller, we have implemented numerous technical and organisational measures to ensure the most complete possible protection of the personal data processed via this website. Nevertheless, Internet-based data transmissions can in principle have security gaps, so that absolute protection cannot be guaranteed. For this reason, each person concerned is free to transmit personal data to us by alternative means, such as telephone.

(7) As a responsible company, we refrain from automatic decision-making or profiling.

## 3\. Your rights

(1) You have the following rights against us with regard to the personal data concerning you:

**– Right of access:**

Every data subject affected by the processing of personal data has the right granted by the GDPR to obtain from the data controller, at any time and free of charge, information about the personal data stored about him and a copy of this information. Furthermore, the European Directive and Regulation Maker has granted the data subject information on the following information:  
a) the purposes of the processing  
b) the categories of personal data processed  
c) the recipients or categories of recipients to whom the personal data have been or will be disclosed, in particular recipients in third countries or international organizations  
d) if possible, the envisaged duration for which the personal data will be stored or, if this is not possible, the criteria for determining such duration  
e) the existence of a right to rectify or erase personal data relating to him or her or to limit the processing carried out by the controller or of a right to object to such processing  
f) the existence of a right of appeal to a supervisory authority  
g) where the personal data are not collected from the data subject: all available information on the origin of the data  
h) the existence of automated decision-making, including profiling, in accordance with Article 22(1) and (4) of the GDPR and, at least in these cases, meaningful information on the logic involved and the scope and intended impact of such processing on the data subject

In addition, the data subject has the right to know whether personal data have been transferred to a third country or to an international organization. If this is the case, the data subject shall also have the right to obtain information on the appropriate safeguards in connection with the transfer.

If a data subject wishes to exercise this right of access, he or she may at any time contact a member of staff of the controller.

**– Right to revoke consent under data protection law:**

Any data subject involved in the processing of personal data has the right to withdraw consent to the processing of personal data at any time.  
If a data subject wishes to exercise this right to withdraw consent, he or she may do so at any time and by any means of communication to an employee of the controller.

**– Right to rectification:**

The data subject shall have the right to obtain from the controller without delay the rectification of inaccurate personal data concerning him or her. Taking into account the purposes of the processing, the data subject shall have the right to request the completion of incomplete personal data, including by means of a supplementary statement.  
If a data subject wishes to exercise this right of access, he or she may at any time contact an employee of the controller.

**– Right to deletion / right to be forgotten:**

The data subject shall have the right to obtain from the controller the erasure without delay of personal data relating to him or her and the controller shall be obliged to erase without delay personal data for any of the following reasons:  
a) the personal data are no longer necessary for the purposes for which they were collected or otherwise processed.  
b) the data subject withdraws the consent on which the processing was based pursuant to Article 6(1)(a) or Article 9(2)(a) and there is no other legal basis for the processing.  
c) the data subject objects to the processing pursuant to Article 21(1) and there are no overriding legitimate reasons for the processing, or the data subject objects to the processing pursuant to Article 21(2).  
d) the personal data have been unlawfully processed.  
e) the erasure of the personal data is necessary to fulfil a legal obligation under Union law or the law of the Member States to which the controller is subject.  
f) the personal data have been collected in relation to information society services offered in accordance with Article 8(1).

If a data subject wishes to exercise this right of cancellation/right to be forgotten, he or she may at any time contact an employee of the controller for this purpose.

If we have made the personal data public and we are obliged to delete them pursuant to Art. 17 (1) GDPR, we shall take appropriate measures, also of a technical nature, taking into account the available technology and the implementation costs, to inform those responsible for data processing who process the personal data that a data subject has requested them to delete all links to this personal data or copies or replications of this personal data. Our employees will take the necessary measures.

**– Right to limit the processing:**

The data subject shall have the right to request the controller to restrict the processing if one of the following conditions is met:  
a) the accuracy of the personal data is contested by the data subject for a period of time which enables the controller to verify the accuracy of the personal data,  
b) the processing is unlawful and the data subject refuses to erase the personal data and instead requests that the use of the personal data be restricted;  
c) the controller no longer needs the personal data for the purposes of the processing, but the data subject needs them for the exercise, exercise or defense of legal rights; or  
d) the data subject has objected to the processing referred to in Article 21(1) before it has been established whether the legitimate reasons of the controller outweigh those of the data subject.

If a data subject wishes to exercise this right to limit the processing, he or she may at any time do so by contacting an employee of the controller.

**– Right to object to the processing:**

Any person concerned by the processing of personal data has the right under the GDPR to object at any time, for reasons related to his/her particular situation, to the processing of personal data concerning him/her under Article 6(1)(e) or (f) of the GDPR. This also applies to profiling based on these provisions.

In the event of objection, we will no longer process the personal data unless we can prove compelling grounds for processing worthy of protection which outweigh the interests, rights and freedoms of the data subject, or the processing serves to assert, exercise or defend legal claims.

If we process personal data for the purpose of direct advertising, the data subject has the right to object at any time to the processing of personal data for the purpose of such advertising. This also applies to profiling as far as it is connected with such direct advertising. If the data subject objects to our processing for direct marketing purposes, we will no longer process the personal data for these purposes.

In addition, the data subject shall have the right to object to the processing of personal data relating to him or her by us for scientific or historical research purposes or for statistical purposes pursuant to Art. 89 (1) GDPR for reasons arising from his or her particular situation, unless such processing is necessary for the performance of a task in the public interest.  
In order to exercise the right to object, the data subject may contact any employee directly. The data subject is also free to exercise his or her right of objection in connection with the use of information society services, notwithstanding Directive 2002/58/EC, by means of automated procedures using technical specifications.

**– Right to data portability:**

The data subject shall have the right to obtain the personal data concerning him which he has provided to a data controller in a structured, common and machine-readable format and shall have the right to communicate such data to another controller without being hampered by the controller to whom the personal data have been provided, provided that  
(a) the processing is based on a consent pursuant to Article 6(1)(a) or Article 9(2)(a) or on a contract pursuant to Article 6(1)(b); and  
(b) the processing is carried out by automated means.

When exercising his/her right to data portability pursuant to Art. 20 para. 1 GDPR, the data subject shall have the right to obtain that the personal data be transferred directly from one controller to another controller, provided that this is technically feasible and that the rights and freedoms of other persons are not impaired.

If a data subject wishes to exercise this right to data transfer, he or she may at any time contact an employee of the controller.

**– Automated individual decision-making, including profiling**

Any person subject to the processing of personal data shall have the right under the GDPR not to be subject to a decision based solely on automated processing, including profiling, which has legal effects on him or her or significantly affects him or her in a similar manner, provided that the decision  
a) is not necessary for the conclusion or performance of a contract between the data subject and the controller; or  
b) is authorized by legislation of the Union or of the Member States to which the controller is subject and contains appropriate measures to safeguard the rights and freedoms and the legitimate interests of the data subject; or  
(c) with the express consent of the data subject.

Where the decision is necessary for the conclusion or performance of a contract between the data subject and the controller or with the express consent of the data subject, we shall take reasonable steps to safeguard the rights and freedoms and the legitimate interests of the data subject, including at least the right to have the data subject intervene, to present his or her views and to challenge the decision.

If the data subject wishes to exercise rights relating to automated decisions, he or she may at any time do so by contacting an employee of the controller.

(2) You also have the right to complain to a data protection supervisory authority about the processing of your personal data by us. The supervisory authority responsible for our company is as follows:

Bayerisches Landesamt für Datenschutzaufsicht  
Promenade 27  
91522 Ansbach  
Germany

Tel.: +49 981 – 53 1300  
E-Mail: poststelle@lda.bayern.de

## 4\. Collection of personal data when visiting our website / cookies

(1) If you only use our website for information purposes, i.e. if you do not register or otherwise provide us with information, we only collect the personal data that your browser transmits to our server. If you wish to view our website, we collect the following data, which is technically necessary for us to display our website to you and to guarantee stability and security (legal basis is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f GDPR):  
– IP address  
– Date and time of the request  
– Time zone difference to Greenwich Mean Time (GMT)  
– Internet service provider of the accessing system  
– Contents of the request (concrete page)  
– Access status/HTTP status code  
– Amount of data transferred in each case  
– Website from which the request comes (referrer)  
– Browser  
– Operating system and its interface  
– Language and version of the browser software.

(2) In addition to the aforementioned data, cookies are stored on your computer when you use our website. Cookies are small text files that are stored on your hard drive assigned to the browser you are using and through which certain information flows to the location that sets the cookie (here by us). Cookies cannot execute programs or transmit viruses to your computer. They serve to make the website more user-friendly and effective.

(3) Use of cookies:  
a) This website uses the following types of cookies, the scope and functionality of which are explained below:  
– Transient cookies (see b)  
– Persistent cookies (see c)  
– Flash-Cookies (f).  
b) Transient cookies are automatically deleted when you close your browser. These include in particular session cookies. They store a so-called session ID, which can be used to assign various requests from your browser to the shared session. This enables your computer to be recognized when you return to our website. The session cookies are deleted when you log out or close your browser.  
c) Persistent cookies are automatically deleted after a specified period, which may vary depending on the cookie. You can delete cookies at any time in the security settings of your browser.  
d) You can configure your browser settings according to your wishes and, for example, refuse to accept third-party cookies or all cookies. We would like to point out that you may not be able to use all the functions of this website.  
e) We use cookies to identify you for subsequent visits if you have an account with us. Otherwise, you will have to log in again for each visit.  
f) The Flash cookies used are not recorded by your browser, but by your Flash plug-in. We also use HTML5 storage objects, which are stored on your end device. These objects store the required data regardless of the browser you are using and do not have an automatic expiration date. If you do not wish the Flash cookies to be processed, you must install an appropriate add-on, e.g. “Better Privacy” for Mozilla Firefox (https://addons.mozilla.org/de/firefox/addon/betterprivacy/) or the Adobe Flash Killer cookie for Google Chrome. You can prevent the use of HTML5 storage objects by using private mode in your browser. We also recommend that you regularly delete your cookies and browser history manually.

## 5\. Further functions and offers of our website

(1) In addition to the purely informational use of our website, we offer various services that you can use if you are interested. For this purpose, you must generally provide further personal data which we use to provide the respective service and to which the aforementioned data processing principles apply.

(2) In some cases, we use external service providers to process your data. These have been carefully selected and commissioned by us, are bound by our instructions and are checked regularly.

(3) The hosting services used by us serve to provide the following services: infrastructure and platform services, computing capacity, storage space and database services, security services and technical maintenance services which we use for the purpose of operating this online service.  
Here we, or our hosting provider, process inventory data, contact data, content data, contract data, usage data, meta data and communication data of customers, interested parties and visitors to this online service on the basis of our legitimate interests in the efficient and secure provision of this online service in accordance with Art. 6 Para. 1 lit. f GDPR in connection with Art. 28 GDPR.

(4) Furthermore, we may pass on your personal data to third parties if we offer participation in promotions, competitions, contracts or similar services together with partners. You will receive further information on this when you enter your personal data or in the description of the offer below.

(5) If our service providers or partners are based in a country outside the European Economic Area (EEA), we will inform you about the consequences of this circumstance in the description of the offer.

## 6\. Data protection for job applications

The data controller collects and processes the personal data of applicants for the purpose of processing the application. Processing may also be carried out electronically. This is particularly the case if an applicant submits the relevant application documents electronically, for example by e-mail or via a contact form on the website, to the controller. If the controller concludes an employment contract with an applicant, the data transmitted shall be stored for the purpose of processing the employment contract in compliance with the statutory provisions. If the controller does not conclude an employment contract with the candidate, the application documents shall be automatically deleted, unless deletion conflicts with any other legitimate interests of the controller. Other legitimate interests in this sense include, for example, the duty to provide evidence in proceedings under the General Equal Treatment Act (Allgemeines Gleichbehandlungsgesetz – AGG).

The processing of the applicant data is carried out to fulfil our (pre)contractual obligations within the scope of the application procedure within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b. GDPR Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f. GDPR insofar as data processing becomes necessary for us, e.g. within the framework of legal proceedings (in Germany, § 26 BDSG additionally applies).

## 7\. Objection or revocation against the processing of your data

(1) If you have given your consent to the processing of your data, you can revoke it at any time and by any means of communication. Such a revocation influences the permissibility of processing your personal data after you have given it to us.

(2) Insofar as we base the processing of your personal data on a weighing of interests, you may object to the processing. This is the case if the processing is in particular not necessary for the fulfilment of a contract with you, which is described by us in the following description of the functions. In the event of such an objection, we ask you to explain the reasons why we should not process your personal data as we have done. In the event of your justified objection, we will examine the situation and either discontinue or adapt the data processing or point out our compelling reasons worthy of protection on the basis of which we will continue the processing.

(3) You may of course object to the processing of your personal data for advertising and data analysis purposes at any time. You can contact us about your advertising objection at the address given in section 2 (2).

## 8\. Legal or contractual provisions for the provision of personal data/ necessity for the conclusion of a contract/ consequences of nonprovision/deletion

(1) We would like to inform you that the provision of personal data is partly required by law. However, it is also possible that a data subject may be required to provide us with personal information in order for a contract to be performed. Failure to do so would result in the contract not being able to be concluded. Our employees will be happy to answer any questions you may have on a case-by-case basis.

(2) The data processed by us will be deleted or their processing restricted in accordance with Art. 17 and 18 GDPR. Unless expressly stated in this data protection declaration, the data stored by us will be deleted as soon as they are no longer required for their intended purpose and there are no legal obligations to retain them. If the data are not deleted because they are required for other and legally permissible purposes, their processing will be restricted. This means that the data will be blocked and not processed for other purposes. This applies, for example, to data that must be stored for commercial or tax reasons.

According to legal requirements, the data is stored in particular for 10 years in accordance with §§ 147 para. 1 AO, 257 para. 1 nos. 1 and 4, para. 4 HGB (German Commercial Code) (books, records, management reports, accounting records, commercial books, documents relevant for taxation, etc.) and 6 years in accordance with § 257 para. 1 nos. 2 and 3, para. 4 HGB (German Commercial Code) (commercial letters).

## 9\. Newsletter

(1) With your consent, you can subscribe to our newsletter, with which we inform you about our current interesting offers. The advertised goods and services are named in the declaration of consent.

(2) We use the so-called double opt-in procedure to register for our newsletter. This means that after your registration we will send you an e-mail to the specified e-mail address in which we will ask you to confirm that you wish to receive the newsletter. If you do not confirm your registration within 24 hours, your information will be blocked and automatically deleted after one month. In addition, we store the IP addresses you use, the computer system you use and the dates of registration and confirmation. The purpose of the procedure is to prove your registration and, if necessary, to clarify any possible misuse of your personal data.

(3) The personal data collected in the course of registering for the newsletter will be used exclusively for sending our newsletter. Furthermore, subscribers to the newsletter may be informed by e-mail if this is necessary for the operation of the newsletter service or registration in this respect, as might be the case in the event of changes to the newsletter offering or changes to the technical conditions. The personal data collected as part of the newsletter service will not be passed on to third parties.

(4) Your e-mail address is the only mandatory information for sending the newsletter. The indication of further, separately marked data is voluntary and will be used to address you personally. After your confirmation we save your e-mail address for the purpose of sending you the newsletter. The legal basis is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. a GDPR.

(5) You can revoke your consent to the sending of the newsletter at any time and cancel your subscription to the newsletter. You may revoke your consent by any means of communication, for example by clicking on the link provided in every newsletter e-mail, by sending an e-mail to info@snapview.de or by sending a message to the contact details given in the imprint.

(6) Newsletter service provider: CleverReach  
The newsletter will be sent by CleverReach GmbH & Co. KG, Mühlenstr. 43, 26180 Rastede, Germany. You can view the data protection regulations of the service provider here: https://www.cleverreach.com/de/datenschutz/. The service provider is used on the basis of our legitimate interests pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f GDPR and an order processing contract pursuant to Art. 28 para. 3 sentence 1 GDPR.

The service provider can use the data of the recipients in pseudonymous form, i.e. without allocation to a user, to optimize or improve its own services, e.g. for technical optimization of dispatch and presentation of the newsletter or for statistical purposes. However, the service provider does not use the data of our newsletter recipients to write to them itself or to pass the data on to third parties.

## 10\. Use of Software, Data on Use

(1) When setting up a user account for the lease license, the following data is requested and stored electronically: name, company and address of the customer, first name and surname of the authorized user for the software, e-mail address, password.

(2) When setting up a user account for the free use of the software, the following data is stored electronically: first name and surname (the use of pseudonyms is permitted), e-mail address, password.

(3) If the software (session) is used by customers with a user account set up, the following data will continue to be stored in order to provide the functions associated with the user account: start and end time of the sessions, display names of the session participants, time of entry and exit of the participants in the sessions and version number of the client software. The data specified in this chapter (“Use of Software”) will continue to be required for the purpose of planning software and server resources.

(4) The legal basis for processing the data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. b GDPR.

## 11\. Vimeo

We have included videos of the platform “Vimeo” of the provider Vimeo Inc., Attention: Legal Department, 555 West 18th Street New York, New York 10011, USA, on our homepage. Vimeo’s privacy policy can be found at: https://vimeo.com/privacy. We point out that Vimeo may use Google Analytics and refer to the privacy policy (https://policies.google.com/privacy) as well as opt-out options for Google Analytics (http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de=en) or the settings of Google for data use for marketing purposes (https://adssettings.google.com/).

## 12\. Online Advertising

**1\. Use of Google AdSense**

(1) This website uses the online advertising service Google AdSense, through which advertising tailored to your interests can be presented to you. We use it to track your interest in displaying advertisements that may be of interest to you in order to make our website more interesting to you. For this purpose, statistical information about you is collected and processed by our advertising partners. These advertisements can be identified by the reference “Google advertisements” in the respective advertisement.

(2) By visiting our website, Google receives the information that you have visited our website. Google uses a web beacon to set a cookie on your computer. The data mentioned under number 4 of this declaration will be transmitted. We have no influence on the data collected, nor are we aware of the full extent of the data collection and the storage period. Your data will be transferred to the USA and evaluated there. If you are logged in with your Google account, your data can be directly assigned to it. If you do not wish to be assigned to your Google profile, you must log out. It is possible that this data may be passed on to third parties and authorities by Google’s contractual partners. The legal basis for the processing of your data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f GDPR. This website does not place any third-party advertisements via Google AdSense.

(3) You can prevent the installation of Google AdSense cookies in various ways: a) by setting your browser software accordingly, in particular by suppressing third-party cookies, you will not receive any third-party ads; b) by deactivating interest-related ads on Google via the link https://www.googlede/ads/preferences, where this setting is deleted if you delete your cookies; c) by disabling the interest-based ads of the providers that are part of the About Ads self-regulatory campaign via the https://www.aboutads.info/choices link, where this setting is deleted if you delete your cookies; d) by permanently disabling it in your Firefox, Internet Explorer, or Google Chrome browsers via the https://www.google.com/settings/ads/plugin link. Please note that in this case you may not be able to make full use of all the functions of this offer.

(4) Further information on the purpose and scope of data collection and processing as well as further information on your rights in this regard and setting options to protect your privacy can be obtained from us: Google Inc. 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountainview, California 94043, USA; Privacy Policy for Advertising: https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/technologies/ads. Google has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.

**2\. Use of Google Ads**

(1) We use the services of Google Ads to draw attention to our attractive offers with the help of advertising media (so-called Google Ads) on external websites. In relation to the data of the advertising campaigns, we can determine how successful the individual advertising measures are. In doing so, we pursue the interest of displaying advertising to you that is of interest to you, of making our website more interesting for you and of achieving a fair calculation of advertising costs.

(2) These advertising media are delivered by Google via so-called “Ad Servers”. We use ad server cookies for this purpose, which can be used to measure certain parameters for measuring success, such as the display of ads or clicks by users. If you access our website via a Google ad, Google Ads stores a cookie on your PC. These cookies usually lose their validity after 30 days and are not intended to identify you personally. For this cookie, the unique cookie ID, number of ad impressions per placement (frequency), last impression (relevant for post-view conversions) and opt-out information (marking that the user no longer wishes to be addressed) are usually stored as analysis values.

(3) These cookies allow Google to recognize your Internet browser. If a user visits certain pages of a Google Ads customer’s website and the cookie stored on their computer has not expired, Google and the customer may recognize that the user clicked on the ad and was directed to that page. Each Google Ads customer is assigned a different cookie. Cookies cannot therefore be tracked through the websites of Google Ads customers. We ourselves do not collect or process any personal data in the aforementioned advertising measures. We only receive statistical evaluations from Google. These evaluations enable us to identify which of the advertising measures used are particularly effective. We do not receive any further data from the use of the advertising media; in particular, we cannot identify users on the basis of this information.

(4) Due to the marketing tools used, your browser automatically establishes a direct connection with Google’s server. We have no influence on the extent and further use of the data collected by Google through the use of this tool and therefore inform you according to our state of knowledge: By integrating AdWords Conversion, Google receives the information that you have called up the relevant part of our website or clicked on an advertisement from us. If you are registered with a Google service, Google can assign the visit to your account. Even if you are not registered with Google or have not logged in, it is possible for the provider to find out and store your IP address.

(5) You can prevent participation in this tracking process in various ways: a) by setting your browser software accordingly, in particular by suppressing third party cookies to prevent you from receiving advertisements from third parties; b) by deactivating cookies for conversion tracking by setting your browser to block cookies from the domain “www.googleadservices.com”, https://www.googlede/settings/ads, this setting being deleted when you delete your cookies; c) by disabling the interest-based ads of the providers that are part of the “About Ads” self-regulatory campaign via the link https://www.aboutads.info/choices, this setting being deleted when you delete your cookies; d) by permanently disabling it in your Firefox, Internet Explorer or Google Chrome browsers via the link https://www.google.com/settings/ads/plugin. Please note that in this case you may not be able to make full use of all the functions of this offer.

(6) The legal basis for the processing of your data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f GDPR. Further information on data protection at Google can be found at https://www.google.com/intl/de/policies/privacy and https://services.google.com/sitestats/de.html. Alternatively, you can visit the website of the Network Advertising Initiative (NAI) at https://www.networkadvertising.org. Google has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.

**3\. Remarketing**

(1) In addition to Google Ads, we use the Google Remarketing application. This is a process with which we would like to address you again. Through this application, you can be shown our advertisements after visiting our website during your further Internet use. This is done by means of cookies stored in your browser, which are used by Google to record and evaluate your usage behavior when you visit various websites. This allows Google to determine your previous visit to our website. According to Google’s own statements, the data collected during remarketing is not merged with your personal data, which may be stored by Google. In particular, according to Google, a pseudonymization is used for remarketing.

(2) The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f) GDPR. Our legitimate interest lies in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our Internet presence.

(3) In order to enable this advertising service, Google stores a cookie with a sequence of numbers on your device during your visit to our website via your Internet browser. This cookie records both your visit and the use of our website in anonymous form. However, personal data is not passed on. If you subsequently visit the website of a third party who also uses Google’s advertising network, it is possible that advertisements will appear which relate to our website or to our offers there.

(4) To permanently deactivate this function, Google offers a browser plug-in for the most common Internet browsers via https://www.google.com/settings/ads/plugin.

(5) The use of cookies by certain providers, e.g. via http://www.youronlinechoices.com/uk/your-ad-choices or http://www.networkadvertising.org/choices/, can also be deactivated by opt-out.

(6) Through cross-device marketing, Google may be able to track your usage patterns across multiple devices, so you may receive interest-based, personalized advertisements even when you switch devices. However, this requires that you have agreed to link your browser history to your existing Google Account.

(7) Google offers more information about Google Remarketing at http://www.google.com/privacy/ads/.

**4\. DoubleClick by Google**

(1) This website also uses the online marketing tool DoubleClick by Google. DoubleClick uses cookies to serve ads relevant to users to improve campaign performance reports or to prevent a user from seeing the same ads more than once. Google uses a cookie ID to track which ads appear in which browser, thereby preventing them from appearing more than once. In addition, DoubleClick may use cookie IDs to collect conversions related to ad requests. This is the case, for example, when a user sees a DoubleClick ad and later uses the same browser to visit the advertiser’s website and make a purchase. According to Google, DoubleClick cookies do not contain personally identifiable information.

(2) Because of the marketing tools used, your browser automatically connects directly to Google’s server. We have no influence on the extent and the further use of the data, which are raised by the employment of this Tool by Google and inform you therefore according to our state of knowledge: By the integration of DoubleClick Google receives the information that you called the appropriate part of our Internet appearance or clicked on one of our advertisements. If you are registered with a Google service, Google can assign the visit to your account. Even if you are not registered with Google or have not logged in, it is possible that the provider may find out and store your IP address.

(3) You can prevent participation in this tracking process in various ways: a) by setting your browser software accordingly, in particular by suppressing third party cookies to prevent you from receiving advertisements from third parties; b) by deactivating cookies for conversion tracking by setting your browser to block cookies from the domain “www.googleadservices.com”, https://www.google.de/settings/ads, where this setting is deleted when you delete your cookies; c) by disabling the interest-based ads of the providers that are part of the “About Ads” self-regulatory campaign via the https://www.aboutads.info/choices link, where this setting is deleted when you delete your cookies; d) by permanently disabling it in your Firefox, Internet Explorer or Google Chrome browsers via the https://www.google.com/settings/ads/plugin link. Please note that in this case you may not be able to make full use of all the functions of this offer.

(4) The legal basis for the processing of your data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f DS-GVO. Further information on DoubleClick by Google can be found at https://www.google.de/doubleclick and https://support.google.com/adsense/answer/2839090, as well as on data protection at Google in general: https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy. Alternatively, you can visit the Network Advertising Initiative (NAI) website at http://www.networkadvertising.org Google has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.

## 13\. Online Shop

(1) The online shop on this website is operated by the partner company of Snapview, cleverbridge AG, Gereonstr. 43-65, 50670 Cologne, Germany, entirely independently and in its own name. For transactions with cleverbridge, cleverbridge’s terms and conditions of contract and privacy policy therefore apply in addition. Snapview will be informed by cleverbridge of the data of the customers which it provides to cleverbridge at the time of conclusion of the contract or which arise in connection therewith, with the exception of bank data. Snapview also stores these data in electronic form for the purpose of maintaining the licensing relationships. This data is as follows: First and last name, company, address, date and time of contract conclusion, date and time the license key was sent, details of the product purchased, VAT identification number, e-mail address, telephone number, fax number, payment method and payment status.

(2) The legal basis for processing the data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. b GDPR.

## 14\. Comments and Posts/Blog

(1) In our blog, in which we publish various contributions on topics related to our activities, you can make public comments. If users leave comments or other contributions, their IP addresses may be changed or deleted on the basis of our legitimate interests within the meaning of Art. 6 Para. 1 lit. f. of the GDPR for 7 days. This is done for our security if someone leaves illegal contents (insults, forbidden political propaganda, etc.) in comments and contributions. In this case we can be prosecuted ourselves for the comment or contribution and are therefore interested in the identity of the author. The comments will not be checked before publication. We reserve the right to delete comments if they are claimed to be illegal by third parties.

(2) In addition, we reserve the right to process the information provided by the user for the purpose of spam detection, on the basis of our legitimate interests pursuant to Art. 6 Para. 1 lit. f. GDPR.

(3) On the same legal basis, we reserve the right, in the case of surveys, to store the IP addresses of the users for their duration and to use cookies in order to avoid multiple votes.

(4) The personal information provided in the course of comments and contributions, any contact and website information as well as the content details will be stored permanently by us until the user objects.

(5) Follow-up comments can be subscribed to by users with their consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a GDPR. Users receive a confirmation email to check whether they are the owner of the email address entered. Users can unsubscribe from ongoing comment subscriptions at any time. The confirmation email will contain information on the cancellation options. For the purposes of proving the users’ consent, we store the registration time and the IP address of the users and delete this information when users unsubscribe from the subscription.

(6) You can cancel the receipt of our subscription at any time, i.e. revoke your consent. We may store the unsubscribed e-mail addresses for up to three years on the basis of our legitimate interests before deleting them in order to be able to prove a previously given consent. The processing of this data is limited to the purpose of a possible defense against claims.

## 15\. Plugins and tools

**1\. Google Web Fonts**

This website uses so-called web fonts provided by Google for the uniform display of fonts. When you call up a page, your browser loads the required web fonts into its browser cache in order to display texts and fonts correctly. For this purpose, the browser you are using must connect to Google’s servers. This enables Google to know that your IP address has been used to access our website. The use of Google Web Fonts is in the interest of a uniform and appealing presentation of our online services. This constitutes a legitimate interest within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f GDPR.

If your browser does not support web fonts, a standard font will be used by your computer. Further information on Google Web Fonts can be found at https://developers.google.com/fonts/faq and in Google’s privacy policy: https://developers.google.com/fonts/faq.

**2\. Use of Google reCAPTCHA**

We use the reCAPTCHA service of Google Inc. (Google) to protect your orders via Internet forms. The query serves to differentiate whether the input is made by a human being or whether it is misused by automated, mechanical processing. The query includes the transmission of the IP address and any other data required by Google for the service reCAPTCHA to Google. For this purpose, your input will be transmitted to Google and used there. By using reCAPTCHA, you agree that the recognition you provide will be incorporated into the digitization of old works. However, if IP anonymization is activated on this website, your IP address will be shortened by Google in advance within member states of the European Union or in other signatory states to the Agreement on the European Economic Area. Only in exceptional cases will the full IP address be transmitted to and truncated by Google on servers in the United States. On behalf of the operator of this website, Google will use this information to evaluate your use of this service. The IP address transmitted by your browser as part of reCAPTCHA is not merged with other data from Google. These data are subject to the differing data protection regulations of Google. For more information about Google’s privacy policy, please visit: https://www.google.com/intl/de/policies/privacy/.

**3\. Use of ajax.googleapis.com and jQuery**

On this page we use Ajax and jQuery technologies to optimize loading speeds. In this respect, program libraries are accessed from Google servers. The CDN (Content delivery network) from Google is used. If you have previously used jQuery on another Google CDN page, your browser will use the cached copy. If this is not the case, it will require downloading, whereby data from your browser will be sent to Google Inc. (“Google”). Your data will be transferred to the USA. You can find out more on the pages of the providers.

The legal basis for the processing of your data is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f GDPR.

**4\. Google Tag Manager**

Google Tag Manager is a solution with which we can manage so-called website tags via a single interface (and thus, for example, integrate Google marketing services into our online offering). The Tag Manager itself (which implements the tags) does not process any personal user data. With regard to the processing of users’ personal data, reference is made to the following information on Google services. Terms of use: https://www.google.com/intl/de/tagmanager/use-policy.html.

**5\. Cloudflare**

To protect the server and IT infrastructure, we work with Cloudflare (https://www.cloudflare.com/) to deploy a web application firewall on our websites. This serves as a filter between our servers and potentially malicious traffic from the Internet. It protects against fraudulent activities such as SQL injections and cross-site scripting. Information about the personal data required for this service can be found at https://blog.cloudflare.com/what-cloudflare-logs/. The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f GDPR. You can view the Cloudflare data protection declaration at https://www.cloudflare.com/privacypolicy/. A data processing contract with Cloudflare and suitable guarantees for data transfers to third countries ensure compliance with data protection.

**6\. Zendesk**

(1) This website uses the Customer Relationship Management (CRM) service of Zendesk Inc., 989 Market Street #300, San Francisco, CA 94102, USA.

(2) The legal basis for the use of this service is Art. 6 I f GDPR – legitimate interest. Our legitimate interest in the use of this service lies in being able to answer user queries quickly and efficiently.

(3) Zendesk will only use your data to forward your inquiries to us. Your data will not be passed on to third parties.

(4) In order to use Zendesk, you must enter at least one correct e-mail address. The service can also be used pseudonymously. In the course of processing service requests, it may be necessary to collect further data (e.g. first name, surname, address, etc.).

(5) The use of Zendesk is optional. If you do not agree with Zendesk collecting your data, we offer you alternative contact options for submitting service requests by telephone or postal mail.

(6) Further information can be found in Zendesk’s Privacy Policy: https://www.zendesk.de/company/customers-partners/privacy-policy/.

## 16\. Social Media

**1\. Use of social media plug-ins / links**

(1) We currently use the following social media plug-ins / links: Facebook, Google+, Twitter, LinkedIn.  
We offer you the possibility to communicate directly with the provider via the button. Only if you click on the marked field and activate it will the provider receive the information that you have called up the corresponding website of our online service. In the case of Facebook, the IP address is anonymized immediately after collection according to the information provided by the respective provider in Germany. Through activation, personal data from you is transmitted to the respective provider and stored there (for US providers in the USA). Since the provider collects the data in particular via cookies, we recommend that you delete all cookies via your browser’s security settings before clicking on the grayed-out box.

(2) We have no influence on the collected data and data processing procedures, nor are we aware of the full scope of data collection, the purposes of processing, the storage periods. We also do not have any information on the deletion of the collected data by the provider.

(3) The provider stores the data collected about you as user profiles and uses these for the purposes of advertising, market research and/or the design of its website to meet requirements. Such an evaluation takes place in particular (also for users who are not logged in) in order to present demand-oriented advertising and to inform other users of the social network about your activities on our website. You have the right to object to the creation of these user profiles, whereby you must contact the respective provider to exercise this right. Through the plug-ins, we offer you the opportunity to interact with social networks and other users so that we can improve our services and make them more interesting for you as a user. The legal basis for the use of the plug-ins is Art. 6 Para. 1 S. 1 lit. f GDPR.

(4) The data transfer takes place regardless of whether you have an account with the provider and are logged in there. If you are logged in with the provider, your data collected by us will be directly assigned to your existing account with the provider. If you click on the activated button and, for example, link the page, the provider also stores this information in your user account and communicates it publicly to your contacts. We recommend that you log out regularly after using a social network, especially before activating the button, as this allows you to avoid assigning your profile to the provider.

(5) Further information on the purpose and scope of data collection and its processing by the provider can be found in the following data protection declarations of these providers. There you will also find further information on your rights in this regard and setting options to protect your privacy.

(6) Addresses of the respective providers and URL with their data protection information:  
a) Facebook Inc., 1601 S California Ave, Palo Alto, California 94304, USA; further information on data collection: https://www.facebook.com/policy.php; https://www.facebook.com/about/privacy/your-info#everyoneinfo. Facebook has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.  
b) Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountainview, California 94043, USA; https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/partners/?hl=de. Google has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.  
c) Twitter, Inc., 1355 Market St, Suite 900, San Francisco, California 94103, USA; https://twitter.com/privacy. Twitter has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.  
d) LinkedIn Corporation, 2029 Stierlin Court, Mountain View, California 94043, USA; https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy. LinkedIn has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US-Framework.

Date: 2019-09-03
